Finding aid to the Northampton and Local History Collection CA.MS.00002
Smith College Archives
Northampton and Local History Collection
1820-1999
Smith College Archives
CA.MS.00002
7.5 linear feet (18 containers)
History of Northampton and its environs. Contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, and publications.
Scope and Contents
The collection was collected by the Smith College Archives over an extended period and included in the subject files are correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, programs and other primary source materials. The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by subject. The collection is not complete, and materials are added to it on a regular basis. For in-depth research pertaining to Northampton and other local history, researchers should contact Historic Northampton, Inc. and the Forbes Library, as they have a greater depth of local history collections.
The College Archives also has books relating to Northampton and surrounding towns.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Northampton and Local History Collection was donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Bibliography
Books about Northampton in the Smith College Archives
Bliss, Arthur Ames. Theodore Bliss, Publisher and Bookseller: A Study of Character and Life in the Middle Period of the XIX Century. Northampton Historical Society, 1914
Brown, E. Francis. Joseph Hawley: Colonial Radical. New York: Columbia University Press, 1903
Clarke, Rev. Solomon. Antiquities, Historicals and Graduates of Northampton. Northampton: Gazette Printing, 1882
Early Northampton. (pub. by the Betty Allen Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution) Springfield: F.A. Bassette Co. 1914
Edwards, William H. Timothy and Rhoda Ogden Edwards of Stockbridge Mass, and their descendants; a genealogy. Cincinatti: The Robert Clarke Co. 1903
Gere, Henry S. Reminiscences of Old Northampton: sketches of the town as it appeared from 1840-1850. [Northampton], 1902
Hawthorne, Hildegarde. Rambles in Old College Towns. New York: Dodd, Mead and Co. 1917
Historical Register and General Directory of Northampton. Northampton: Gazette Printing Co. 1875-76
Johnson, Clifton. Historic Hampshire in the Connecticut Valley; happenings in a charming old New England county from the time of the dinosaurs down to about 1900. Springfield: Milton Bradley, 1932
Knab, Frederick. 1902-1903: Northampton of Today, depicted by pen and camera. Northampton: Picturesque Publishing Company, 1902
The Meadow City's Quarter Millennial Book, a Memorial of the Celebration of the two-hundred and fiftieth anniversary of the Settlement of the town of Northampton, Massachusetts. June 5-7, 1904
The Northampton Book: Chapters from three hundred years in the life of a New England Town, 1654-1954. (pub. by the tercentenary committee) Brattleboro: Alan S. Browne, Inc. 1954
Northampton, The Meadow City. Northampton: Kneeland and Bryant, 1894
Northampton and the Northampton Institute for Savings, 1842-1942. Northampton: Metcalf Printing and Publishing Co. Inc. 1942
Trumble, James Russell. History of Northampton, Mass. from its settlement in 1654. Northampton: Press of Gazette Printing, 1902
Well, Daniel White and Ruben Field Wells. A History of Hatfield, Mass. 1660-1910. Springfield: F.C.H. Gibbons, 1910.
Northampton (Mass.)--History--Sources.
- Anniversaries, 1904 (Box 1)
- Anniversaries, 1954 (Box 1)
- Arcadia Wildlife Sanctuary, 1944 -; undated (Box 1)
- Banks, 1904 - (Box 1)
- Bart's Ice Cream, 1986 - (Box 1)
- Charity, 1998 (Box 1)
- Churches - general, 1882 - (Box 1)
  - Baptist Church, 1902 - (Box 1)
  - Edwards Church, 1965; undated (Box 1)
  - First Congregational Church, undated (Box 1)
  - St. John's Episcopal Church, 1895 -; undated (Box 1)
  - St. Mary's Catholic Church, c1895 - (Box 1)
  - Unitarian Society, 1982; undated (Box 1)
- Cider Mill (Box 1)
  General
  See Mills
- City Hall, 1888 -; undated (Box 1)
- Clubs
  - Hampshire Choral Society, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Hampshire County Progressive Club, 1928 - (Box 1)
  - Home Culture Club
    See Organizations: People's Institute
  - Monday Afternoon Club, 1941 -; undated (Box 1)
  - Musical Societies (misc.), 1873 -; undated (Box 1)
  - Northampton Choral Club, 1898 -; undated (Box 1)
  - Northampton Women's Club, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Northampton Social and Literary Club, 1925 - (Box 1)
  - Round Hill Club, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Travelers' Club, 1996 (Box 1)
- Cooley Dickinson Hospital (Box 1)
  See Hospitals
- Disasters (Box 2)
  - Blizzards, 1888 - (Box 2)
  - Floods, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Floods, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Hurricanes, 1938 (Box 2)
- Film Festivals, 1999 (Box 2)
- Florence, 1976 -; undated (Box 2)
- Florence Sewing Machine Company, 1864; undated (Box 2)
- General
  - Clippings, 1879 -; undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1882 -; undated (Box 2)
- Hadley, 1942 -; undated (Box 2)
- Haydenville, 1975 - (Box 2)
- Historical Pageant, 1911 (Box 2)
- Hockanum Ferry, 1889 -; undated (Box 2.1)
- Holyoke, 1906 -; undated (Box 2.1)
- Hospitals (Box 2.1)
  - Cooley Dickinson, 1906 -; undated (Box 2.1)
  - State Hospital, 1904 -; undated (Box 2.1)
- Hotels - General, 1893 -; undated (Box 2.1)
  - Hotel Northampton and Wiggins Tavern, 1940 -; undated (Box 2.1)
  - Plymouth Inn, 1990 (Box 2.1)
  - Rose Tree Inn, 1914 -; undated (Box 2.1)
  - Round Hill Hotel, 1874 -; undated (Box 2.1)
- Individuals -- General, A-Z, 1959; undated (Box 3)
  See also: Individual: George M. Roberts scrapbook 1878-1881
  - Burleigh, Charles C., 1962- (Box 3)
  - Clarke, Christopher, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Coolidge, Grace, 1989 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Copeland, undated (Box 3)
  - Dickinson, Emily, 1976 - (Box 3)
  - Edwards, Jonathon, 1937 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Graham, Dr. Sylvester P., 1976 (Box 3)
  - Kneeland, Harriet J., 1902 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Mather, Rev. Eleazer, 1898 (Box 3)
  - Nute, May, 1907 (Box 3)
  - Parsons Family, 1929 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Pratt, William F., 1996 (Box 3)
  - Seymour, undated (Box 3)
  - Stoddard, Rev. Solomon, undated (Box 3)
  - Watson Family, 1995 (Box 3)
- Leeds, 1975 - (Box 3)
- Libraries
  - Clarke Library (Box 3)
    See Memorial Hall
  - Forbes Library (Box 3)
    - History, 1894 -; undated (Box 3)
    - Photographs, 1896 -; undated (Box 3)
- The Manse, 1922 -; undated (Box 3)
- Maps (Box 3)
  See Publications: Maps and Guides
- Memorial Hall / Clarke Library, undated (Box 3)
- Mills, 1936 -; undated (Box 3)
- Mount Holyoke
  - Photographs, c1890 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Prospect House, 1863 -; undated (Box 3)
- Mount Nonotuck, 1890; undated (Box 3)
- Mount Sugarloaf, 1899 (Box 3)
- Mount Tom, 1893 -; undated (Box 3)
  - Summit House, 1898 -; undated (Box 3)
- Ox Bow, c1890 -; undated (Box 3)
- Individual: George M. Roberts scrapbook, 1878-1881 (Box 4)
- Forbes Library (Box 5)
  - Reports 1-20, 1895-1914 (Box 5)
  - Forbes Library, The Half Century, 1945 (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1905; 1950-1966 (Box 5)
  - A Guide to Fine Arts in the Forbes Library, 1884-1994 (Box 5)
  - Account Books, 1906-1911 (Box 5)
- Organizations (Box 6)
  - Council of Social Agencies, 1996 (Box 6)
  - Historic Northampton, 1940 -; undated (Box 6)
    - Calendar and Newsletter, 1996 - (Box 6)
  - Home Culture Club, 1887 -; undated (Box 6)
  - Northampton Social and Literary Club, undated (Box 6)
  - People's Institute - General, 1909 -; undated (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1927 -; undated (Box 6)
    - Dramatics, 1923 -; undated (Box 6)
    - Photographs, 1931 -; undated (Box 6)
    - Individuals, 1896 - (Box 6)
    - Smith College, 1910 -; undated (Box 6)
    - James House (Girl's City Club), 1928; undated (Box 6)
  - United Way, 1996; undated (Box 6)
    - Smith Charities, undated (Box 6)
- Parks (Box 7)
  - Child's Park, 1989; undated (Box 7)
  - Look Park, 1942- (Box 7)
  - Pulaski Park, 1976 (Box 7)
- Parking, Smith College, 1998 (Box 7)
- Pass at Thermopylae, 1895; undated (Box 7)
- Publications
  - Maps and Guides, 1900; undated (Box 7)
  - Maps and Guides (Trolley), 1903 - (Box 7)
  - Newspapers, 1936 - (Box 7)
  - The Northampton Book, undated (Box 7)
  - Northampton Poets, 1948 (Box 7)
  - This is Northampton, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - River Gods, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Views of Northampton and Smith College, 1904 (Box 7)
  - Drives in Northampton and Vicinity, 1888 (Box 7)
  - Northampton Picturesque, 1893 (Box 7)
  - Northampton and Smith College, undated (Box 7)
  - College Shopper and Smacker, Spring; 1926 (Box 7)
  - Northampton, Mass., undated (Box 7)
  - Western New England, Oct. 1911 (Box 7)
  - Northampton, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Mount Tom; an All Outdoors Magazine (Box 8)
    - Volumes 1-7, 1905-1914 (Box 8)
    - Volume 10, nos. 1and 2, 1917 (Box 8)
- Railroad Stations, 1886 -; undated (Box 9)
- Restaurants, 1976 -; undated (Box 9)
  See also: Hotels
- Rivers
  - Connecticut River, 1901 - (Box 9)
  - Mill River, 1897 -; undated (Box 9)
- Salem, Ma., undated (Box 9)
- Sanitary Wagon, 1890 -; undated (Box 9)
- Schools
  - General, 1974 -; undated (Box 9)
  - Mary A. Burnham School, 1877 -; undated (Box 9)
    - Photographs, 1879 -; undated (Box 9)
  - Stoneleigh - Burnham School, c1879 - (Box 9)
  - Capen School - general, 1908 -; undated (Box 9)
    - Photographs, 1889 -; undated (Box 9)
    - Photograph Albums, 1913 - 1914; undated (Box 9)
    - Yearbooks, 1898 (Box 9)
  - Clarke School, 1913 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Hill School, 1991 (Box 10)
  - Northampton Commercial College, undated (Box 10)
  - Northampton High School, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Northampton Junior College, 1946 - (Box 10)
  - Northampton School for Girls, undated (Box 10)
  - Round Hill School, 1891 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Smith Academy, 1958 (Box 10)
  - Smith Vocational School, 1978 (Box 10)
    - Auto-mechanics Course, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Sunnyside, 1998 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Sheldon House, 1998 (Box 10)
- Streets - general, c1876 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Barrett Place, 1997 (Box 10)
  - College Lane, c1891 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Elm Street, 1993 - (Box 10)
    - Photographs, c1876 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Green Street, 1893 -; undated (Box 10)
  - Main Street - general, 1975 -; undated (Box 10)
    - Engravings, 1842 -; undated (Box 10)
    - Photographs, 1860 -; undated (Box 11)
  - Paradise Road, 1891 -; undated (Box 11)
  - Prospect Street, 1887 -; undated (Box 11)
  - Round Hill Road, 1820 -; undated (Box 11)
  - West Street, 1995 -; undated (Box 11)
- Taste of Northampton
  See Restaurants
- Titan's Pier, 1894 -; undated (Box 11)
- Town Hall
  See City Hall
- Underground Railroad, 1974 (Box 11)
- Water Cure, 1848 -; undated (Box 11)
- Whately Glen, c1892 (Box 11)
- Williamsburg, 1963 (Box 11)
- Winter Festival, 1975 (Box 11)
- Theatres, A - Z (Box 11.1)
  - The Calvin, 1996 (Box 11.1)
  - Circle Players, 1959 (Box 11.1)
  - City Hall, 1888 (Box 11.1)
  - History, 1891 -; undated (Box 11.1)
  - Little Theatre, 1915 -; undated (Box 11.1)
  - Opera House, 1881 - (Box 11.1)
  - Players - General, 1913 -; undated (Box 11.1)
    - "The Darling of the Gods", undated (Box 11.1)
    - "The Vanguard", undated (Box 11.1)
    - "When Beauty Pulled the Strings", undated (Box 11.1)
  - Players--Personnel
    - Bunstelle, Judy, 1912 - 1919 (Box 11.1)
    - Burbank, Edith, undated (Box 11.1)
    - Campbell, Stella Patrick, undated (Box 11.1)
    - Mayo, Martha, undated (Box 11.1)
    - Murnane, Allan, 1915 (Box 11.1)
    - Rennie, James, 1915 -; undated (Box 11.1)
    - Taylor, Julia, undated (Box 11.1)
  - Plaza, undated (Box 11.1)
  - Academy of Music (Box 11.2)
    - Deed, 1892 (Box 11.2)
    - General, 1990 -; undated (Box 11.2)
    - Photographs, 1891 -; undated (Box 11.2)
    - Productions, 1891 - 1910 (Box 11.2)
    - Productions, 1911-1920 (Box 11.3)
    - Productions, 1921 - (Box 11.4)
- Books (Box 11.5, Box 11.6)